hey what's up guys my name is the
Chennai welcome back to my C++ series so
today were going to be talking about
what happens when we have data that may
or may not be there a lot of the times
we have like a function that for example
returns data let's just say we're
reading a file but what happens if the
file could not be read what happens if
we couldn't load the file if it's not
present if the data just isn't in the
format that we expect we still need to
return something from the function now a
lot of the time in that particular
scenario you might just return an empty
string but that's not really that great
because it doesn't make much sense I
mean what if the file was just empty
there should be a way for us to actually
see if the data was present or if the
data wasn't present and that's where STD
optional comes in so as to the optional
is new in C++ 17 and it's gonna be like
a part of like a three-part miniseries
in which we cover three different
classes three different new types that
Sables gives us to deal with data that
either may or may not be there or is of
a type that we're not sure about so
let's jump in and take a little bit of a
look at some code that could be written
one way but now with SED optional we
have a better way of dealing with data
that may or may not be there so this is
going to be a super simple example I'm
starting with absolutely no code at all
and what I'm gonna do is write a little
function which reads a file so this will
basically be like read string from file
right or maybe we'll rename it to read
file as string so this should return the
entire file for example as a string so
we'll take in a Const STD string file
path and then over here we'll just have
an input file stream we'll take in the
file path of what we actually want to
read I'll just quickly include F stream
and yes I will make a video soon about
how to read files and see if I suppose I
know I haven't done that yet and now
that we have our input file stream what
we want to do is read it if it's valid
if the file was open successfully or if
it wasn't we have to handle that as well
so very simply we can just write if
stream and then we'll read the file here
and then eventually we'll just close
that file stream however if it didn't
work out right we need to handle that as
well so usually we might do that and
like if I just write this code a bit
differently we would basically return
our string that we read so let's just
say we had an STD string with our
results and then we basically read that
file over here and then we returned our
result right that would be what it would
be like if it were successful and then
if it's not successful well what do we
return right we could just return an
empty string or we could return a string
constructed like this which is the same
exact result but the point is it's kind
of hard for us to know if that file was
open successfully or not because you can
imagine if we have our data here and
it's our rate file as string and we have
our file path which is let us say dot
adult text if we have that here what how
do we check if that was open
successfully well we we basically have
to do something like if data doesn't
equal nothing right and then treated is
that that's that's not nice at all what
I would much prefer is some way of
actually knowing if that data was read
successfully or not because again maybe
that file was there but it was empty
that might be valid we need a way to
know if it's not valid and so another
solution might be to basically have this
output boolean right which was you know
a success let's just say right it's a
boolean that we passed by reference is
going to be our output variable so I
might call it our success and then if
the stream was opened you know it will
set success to true and we'll return
that otherwise we'll success well that
success to false and we'll basically
just return an empty string
so in that case instead of doing this we
need to take in a boolean which is
basically file open successfully and
then we simply pass that into here right
and then we can check that
and that obviously reads a lot better
than an empty string however it's still
not particularly nice so that is where
STD optional can help us a City optional
which we can include by just including
the optional header file here is
basically exactly what it sounds like
it's optional as to whether or not the
data is present so we changed this to be
STD optional and then of course we still
have our string as our type that is
optional and you can see that is giving
me an error here saying that namespace
STD has no remember optional as I
mentioned earlier this is a C++ 17
feature so make sure that you go into
your settings into your compiler
settings
switch your language version to C++ 17
and then now what we do is we still
treat everything as it was before and
somehow I removed the F stream include
for some reason so we still do
everything that we did before or I will
get rid of this our success boolean we
don't need that anymore
and then instead of returning an empty
string what we can do is return an empty
as silly optional and you can do that
just by having curly brackets like this
and then if we want our string to be
returned we simply return result and you
can see it's really that simple and then
if we scroll down into main here we
don't need this anymore
we don't need this we change this to be
an STD optional STD string right or
optionally you could use order right
that's also fine and then what we do is
we just check data dot has value and if
has value is true that means that
optional has been set and we can
basically we'll just log out to the
console file up read successfully and by
the way just a quick note while I was
editing this video this is future Cherno
talking you can also just right if data
because there's a bull operator so
instead of having to write data has
value if data is also totally legit and
I think it looks even cleaner and nicer
anyway back to pasture no otherwise if
it doesn't have value then we know that
that file was not read successfully so
file could not be opened okay so we have
two different branches here based on
whether or not that data was actually
set on and of course to access it we
have a bunch of ways to access it as
well we can simply use data and an error
and then we just have our string there
we can also simply dereference a string
so we'll say this is our string and it's
just basically data dereference like
that and we can access it as a normal
string so it's much the same as a smart
pointer in terms of if you want to
actually access that data and in fact I
think there's also a data dot value
which you can use so let's test this out
and see if that works what I'll do is
just create a dummy file here I'll make
sure that I'm in show all files and just
in sandbox
I will create a new file and I'll just
call it data dot txt we might just throw
in some data into here and then here it
is in my solution Explorer what I'll do
is try and load it so there's data text
of course if I hit I'll just throw in a
little C in yet here so that I'll
console doesn't close immediately and
we'll just run this program you can see
the file was read successfully now let's
just say that file didn't exist I'll go
ahead and delete it
we'll hit f5 and you can see that it
says file cannot be opened so easily now
we're able to switch on whether or not
that file was read successfully now
there's one other really useful thing
that we can do with this let's just say
that we're trying to read the file and
we don't really care too much about
whether or not the file was read or not
like as in we still care about it but
it's not the end of the world if the
file couldn't be opened because if the
file couldn't be opened or if that
particular section of the file wasn't
set or wasn't read maybe we have a
default value for it that's also quite
common so what we can actually do is
have a city string value and we can set
this to data dot value or alright and
what this will do is exactly what it
sounds like if the if the data is
actually present in that SV optional it
will return to us that string if it's
not it will return whatever value we
pass in here so we can say you know not
present for example right this is really
useful for if you're actually pausing
files and trying to for example extract
like variables or any kind of elements
that have been set because quite often
you might have something that is
literally optional to have in the file
and if a certain parameter was not set
in the file you can go with a default
value of what you specify here this is
so useful because for example we could
just simply have an int here count for
example maybe we're trying to run a
benchmark and in the file it says how
many times are on the benchmark now if
this was present in the file we can
extract that count right by just calling
counts dot value or if it wasn't present
we can go with the default value of a
hundred and you can see how we can do
that because this case this would come
from the file so let's
start out as well what we'll do is we
will log that value and of course since
the file does not exist what we should
see in this case I'll just log and end
line as well what we should see in this
case is not present as you can see
that's what we get not present because
the file couldn't be opened all right so
I hope you guys enjoyed this video
hopefully it helped you out as to be
optional as I mentioned it's incredibly
useful and you can see that it really
does help kind of simplify your code and
hopefully let you produce more readable
code if you guys enjoyed this video you
can also help support everything that I
do here on youtube by going to patreon
account for slash the show no huge thank
you as always to all the patrons that
make these videos possible leave a
comment below on what you want to see me
cover next I do have a very long list of
course and as I mentioned earlier sed
Baran and STV Annie are on that list as
well super useful symbols well 17 is
actually such a great release
I might actually make a video on my
favorite C++ 17 features so if you're
not subscribe to make sure that you do
that so that you don't miss that and I
will see you guys next time goodbye
[Music]